Hello everyone, welcome.
Today we're going
to talk about physiology
of cardiac cycle
part one and I'm Vishwa
Rajgopalan. I'm an
associate professor in
biomedical sciences.
So in this session, we will
look into the following
session or learning
objectives. One, to explain
the pressure and volume
changes during each
and every phase of cardiac
cycle, including atrial
and ventricular systole
or diastolic scenarios.
And then we'll talk about
valve condition, how does
the heart valve, what is
its position and what does
it do. And we'll talk
about EKG, we'll talk about
heart sounds and then mapping
all these various events
in an integrative fashion.
okay so well more to the
first slide which is an
introduction to case study
we won't go into the case
study at this time because
after we learn all the you
know the the foundational
concepts then towards the
end of the second session
we will look into the
case study but I want you
to take a quick look at it
about a patient coming to
an ER with some symptoms
such as dyspnea, syncope,
an adult old patient,
chest pain, etc.
and poorly managed
hypercholesterolemia with a long
history of hypertension.
And he has some clinical
results from EKG, left
axis deviation, ST segment
is normal lungs are
clear systolic murmur is
heard loudest over the
aorta look at the blood
pressure which is not high
x-ray is showing some large
lv and calcification of
aortic valve ultrasound
left ventricular
hypertrophy and greatly
increased velocity of
flow during the systolic
portion of the
cardiac cycle but
the cardiac enzymes are normal
if you don't
understand all these
terminologies it is still okay
you will learn about all
these things over this
block the cardiovascular
block but we will
also touch upon this towards
the end of the second
session when we go over
this question but I
want to keep this really
keep thinking about it
as you go along learning
the various concepts
okay normal adult heart
rate as you have some idea
about this 60 to 100
beats per minute 60 to 90.
But the key point is this.
Cardiac electrical activity,
excuse me, leads to cardiac
muscle contraction. That
leads to cardiac cardiovascular
blood circulation.
Cardiac cycle, how do
you define that? All of
the electrical and
mechanical events that occur
within one single heartbeat,
which includes diastole
and systole. Again, it's
all of the electrical
event and mechanical
event that occur in a
single heartbeat and every
heartbeat thereafter.
Okay, so this is a beating
heart alongside what we
call as a Vickers diagram.
We are going to talk about
this we got this diagram
pretty much on most of the
session and as you see the
on the x-axis is time y
-axis is different waveforms
and the heart is beating
at diff at every in a
microsecond of the beating time
point the different things
are happening in the heart
and we're going to look at
all these things in a in
a in in a graphical manner
okay okay before we get
into that we need to
understand something about the
pressures what are the
normal pressures in the heart
chambers and as you can
see here they are not equal
across the different chambers
and how do they differ
now in the if you look at
the LV LV has the highest
blood pressure I say blood
pressure blood pressure
is typically used the
terminology is used for aorta
blood but it's ventricular
pressure pressure rather
I stand corrected so the
systolic the upper number
the systolic pressure
is is on the higher end
higher end in the sense the
highest among the different
chambers it is still in
the normal range 100 to
140 the societies keep
evolving in terms of the what
is the upper limit but I
would say 100 to 120 is
also it can be considered
in the reasonable range
so with the LB pressures
this is the systolic normal
and the diastolic look
at how low it is that is
normal 3 to 12 within the
left ventricle. When the
blood pushes out of the
left ventricle in the aorta,
look at the systolic
remains the same but
diastolic significantly
increases to this new
normal and this
continues to be the blood
pressure that we check
using the sphigma
manometer or any of the
modern devices variants.
And in the right ventricle
we see that the systolic
is on the lower end
comparatively and the
diastolic is also lower than
the LV in the RV compared
to the LV and this
systolic of the right
ventricle is similar to
the pulmonary systolic and
the diastolic of pulmonary
is slightly higher than
the right ventricle
diastolic somewhat close to
the LV diastolic now that's
about LV RV and TA now
the atrium it's significantly
on the lower end so
it's average pressures so
LA is 2 to 10 and RA is 2
to 8 close to one another
but LA is slightly higher
so this is the range and
LA's pressure is close
to the pulmonary capillary
wedge pressure which is
the pressure that can be
measured using a Swann-Gans
catheter in a catheterization
laboratory. Okay.
Now, although the events on
the two sides of the heart,
the right and left sides
of the heart are similar,
they are somewhat asynchronous.
The right atrial systole,
for example, precedes the
left atrial systole and
contraction of the right
ventricle starts after that of
the left. So, these small
subtle variations do happen,
but if you look at And when
these are measured over a
period of minutes, the output
of the left and the right
ventricles are of course
equal. Output means the left
ventricular cardiac output
that goes from LV to aorta
and the right ventricular
cardiac output that goes
from RV to PA. when both are
measured they are close to
one another okay even
though there are subtle very
subtle variations okay with
that in mind we will also
touch upon briefly on the
valves okay what happens with
the valves the at the
beginning of the ventricular
systole ventricular systole
means ventricles contract that's
most important event for
many because that is what
is going to decide the cardiac
output that is what the
blood that's going to go
through the aorta and perfuse
all the parts of the body
with oxygenated blood right
so that the beginning of
the ventricular systole the
the atrioventricular
valves example
the mitral valve
close okay Now,
the AV valves close and
open passively, that is,
they close when a backward
pressure gradient pushes
the blood backward, and they
open when a forward pressure
gradient forces the blood
in the forward direction.
if you look at the valves
themselves by the way in
the left side of the slide
we have the mitral valve
here and the aortic valve
here aortic valve has
three cusps and the mitral
valve has two cusps so
that's why mitral valves are
called bicuspid valve now
these are papillary muscles
muscular structures that
connect to the inner walls
of the left ventricle,
and then these papillary
muscles are connected to
the valves, mitral valve,
using caudate tendinine.
So what happens is the
valves are pulled inward
toward the ventricles
by papillary muscles
to prevent their
bulging too far backward
toward the atria during
ventricular contraction.
So papillary muscles
contract when the ventricular
muscles contract, but contrary
to what might be expected,
they don't help in closing
of the valves. Instead they
pull the veins of the
valves inward toward the
ventricles to prevent their
bulging too far backward toward
the atria during ventricular
contraction. Now if a
cardia tendini becomes ruptured
in a clinical condition
and let's say a patient has
MI, myocardial infarction,
aka heart attack, and if
the papillary muscles or um
excuse me the caudate tendine
becomes ruptured even one
of the papillary muscles
becomes you know paralyzed
because low blood flow as
seen in myocardial infarction
what happens in that
situation the valve bulges far
backward into the atria right
if it bulges far backward
during the ventricular
contraction sometimes so far
that it leaves severely and
results in it can even lead
to severe lethal cardiac
incapacity okay that is a key
point to remember all right
with that let's move on.
Two,
a little more background.
Cardiac cycle,
the atrial and the LA and
the RA contraction precedes
ventricular contraction.
Point number one, the delay in
signal transmission of the
AV node helps pump blood
into the ventricles before
the strong ventricular
contraction begins. This small
delay it is important so that
the there is the atrial
contraction will precede the
ventricular contraction okay
now the systole and diastole
have slightly different
timings and not super
significant at the resting
condition two-thirds of the cardiac
cycle is spent in diastole
this is important two
-thirds of the cardiac cycle
is spent in diastole and only
a third of the cardiac cycle
is spent in systole this
is considering both atrial
and ventricular. And as the
activity increases from
rest, more and more time is
spent in systole and less
time in diastole. All right.
Okay, we've landed in the
Vigors diagram, right? Carl
Vigors is a great scientist,
and he designed this
in a graphical manner.
So horizontally, in the x
-axis we have time and y-axis
we have various different
various different curves
if you look at the broken
black curve it's aortic
pressure and the red
solid one is ventricular
pressure and the middle
broken black is atrial
pressure and the blue is
ventricular volume and this
is EKG or ECG and this is
phonochardiogram which with
which we can hear the heart
sounds right using the
auscultatory stethoscope okay so
now moving on let's look into
what happens in different
phases of the cardiac
cycle the story begins with
atrial systole atrial systole
means the contraction of
the atria the image on to
right will help you understand
what is how does the heart
look you know and the
arrow marks say indicate
like a contractile setting
the green here atria are
contracting both atria left
and the right but for our
discussion we will primarily
talk about the left right is
going to be similar although
remember the pressures
are lower on the right so
we'll highlight mostly on
the left side so atrial
systole what happens in atrial
systole first thing that
happens is depolarization you
would have already learned
about the electrical
conduction depolarization etc
if not you will so
depolarization of the sinoatrial
node is what first that
happens it is not detected
obviously in ekg Instead,
what you see in the EKG is a P
wave. A P wave is the atrial
depolarization in EKG. It
is required and always
precedes atrial contraction.
Now, where is atrial
contraction? Atrial contraction
is indicated by the
pressure waveform. EKG
is the electrical waveform
and contraction or
relaxation is studied using
the pressure waveform.
this is this atrp now
this red a indicates the
atrial contraction waveform
but before that you see
the p wave appears this
is p wave okay and the p
wave appears so p wave
precedes a wave in the atrial
pressure curve by about
0.1 seconds so precedence
is the more important thing
for you to understand.
Again, cardiac electrical
activity precedes the
mechanical activity.
Mechanical activity by
that we mean either
contraction or relaxation.
Okay, alright, let's move on.
That's atrial system.
What else happens in
atrial system? Atrial
contraction
contributes to about 10
milliliters approximately
of the LV blood.
Out of about 140 ml,
only 10 ml comes from
atrial contraction.
What does that mean? Rest
of all the blood comes
from atria to ventricle
via atrial relaxation
which is atrial diastole
phase which we will
see right after this in
the next coming slide.
It acts like a primer
pump as much as about 20%,
maximum it can go up
to about 20%. And then
this even though it looks
like a small number,
it becomes more
important whenever there
is a pathological
condition such as
fibrillation. When
atria is fibrillating,
what does fibrillation
mean? It's irregular
rapid, erratic, non-rhythmic
beating of the atria.
By the way, atrial
fibrillation is
considered to be the
most common arrhythmia
that you can see in
general population.
Many people may not even
realize that they may have
atrial fibrillation. And
that is not good because
atrial fibrillation can have
deleterious consequences
including stroke and other
conditions, heart failure.
So,
and in such situations,
atrial contraction
becomes important
because in fibrillation,
it is not going to, atria
is not going to deliver
as much as it should to
the left ventricle. Okay,
so that's about systole.
Let's move on to
diastole. What happens?
Diastole is happening
during ventricular
systole and much of the
ventricular diastole.
What does that mean?
From here to here is atrial
systole. okay and from
everything else until the
next atrial systole begins
which means from here all
the way till here right look
the next A starts so just
before the next A starts
until then it's atrial
diastole okay this is atrial
systole as it is written and
everything else from here
from this point onward until
this point it is atrial
diastole so that's why
it says during it happens
during ventricular systole
which means during ventricular
systole this phase is
ventricular systole okay this
phase is ventricular
systole and this phase is
ventricular diastole which
means atrial diastole happens
while the ventricle is
contracting atrial diastole
happens while the ventricle
is relaxing okay it may
be sometimes hard to imagine
how it works but that's
how the heart works things
happen kind of simultaneously
in the heart atria
continues to relax while the
ventricle is beating okay
while the ventricle is
receiving blood and while
the ventricle is you know
contracting as well and what's
the next point The LA diastolic
pressure is greater than
RA diastolic pressure.
We saw that in the
previous slide when
we talked about
different pressures in
the different
chambers of the heart.
But both are on the lower end.
And the diastolic blood
flow into the atria
from the veins are due
to pressure difference.
So the vena cavae, for
example the superior vena
cava or the pulmonary veins
for the left side vena
cava superior vena cava
for the right side and the
pulmonary veins on the
left side their pressure is
slightly higher than the
right atrial left atrial
pressure so because of the
pressure difference it's
the blood is you know
understandably flowing from
the veins pulmonary veins
to the right atrium and
from there it will in
diastole will go to the left
ventricle and the right
ventricle respectively.
Alright,
let's move on.
What else is happening
in diastole? When the
atrioventricular valves
open, the small diastolic
pressure difference permits
the blood to flow from
atria into the ventricles.
Where does atrioventricular
valve open? Ok, now for
that we will go to the
we were we are entering
into the systolic phase
but yes we remember even
though we are talking about
we are going to the systolic
phase we're not really
getting into the ventricular
systolic phase because
everything other than this
phase is atrial uh diastole
right so all these are atrial
diastole okay so that's what
we are talking about
when the air when the
atrioventricular valves
open excuse me here
is the atrioventricular
valve open. Okay,
atrioventricular valve opens.
When that happens, when
the atrioventricular valve
opens, the small diastolic
pressure difference
permits the blood to
flow from atria to the
ventricles. So atrial pressure
is slightly higher than
the ventricular pressure,
diastolic pressure.
Okay, atrial diastolic
pressure is slightly higher
than the ventricular
diastolic pressure and that
pushes the blood from
atria to the ventricles in
diastole and remember
again repeating it most of
the atrial blood enters
the ventricle during atrial
diastole I hope so far
this is clear okay atrial
systole and everything else
is atrial diastole until
the next atrial systole
begins and then here this
point is atrial ventricular
valve opening or the
bicuspid valve and
the mitral valve and
there the small pressure
difference helps
okay let's move on atrial
pressure waves all right
atrial what are atrial
pressure waves you see this
a c x v y these are
different pressure wave forms
and they're clinically
relevant and important too okay
that's why we are even
talking about it let's see
what they are first a wave
a wave we already saw a
A wave is detected when
you place a catheter, let's
say in the right atrium
through the jugular vein.
If you go through the jugular
vein, which is commonly
used, and you place the
catheter in the right atrium.
Placing the catheter in
the left atrium is not as
common, it is possible.
But for practical purposes,
let's assume the catheter
is in the left atrium. Okay,
and if you place the
catheter, you can see atrial
contraction pressure wave,
which is the A wave, atrial
systole, due to, why does
it happen? Small increase
in atrial pressure from
the atrial contraction.
All right, the next immediate
pressure waveform is C
-wave. C-wave is happening
due to atrial diastole. We
already saw the atrial diastole
begins right from here.
So just after the peak of
the QRS complex, look at
the QRS complex. This is
QRS, this is Q, this is
R, this is S of the EKG.
Right after the peak of
the QRS, you start seeing
the C-wave. And it results
from a slight increase
in atrial pressure due to
atrial compression during
ventricular contraction.
ventricular contraction has
is beginning now because
the ventricular contraction
is beginning and happening
that results in a slight
increase in atrial pressure
due to atrial compression
because ventricular contraction
is pretty forceful that
leads to some compression
of the atria that leads to
a small bump in the waveform
here to see and x is because
atrial relaxation atria
is beginning to relax now
because atrial diastole
has begun as we talked so
atrial diastole is beginning
so X descent is seen okay
now ACX we have seen what's
V wave look at V here right
V wave happens again still
during diastole all this
is diastole okay atrio
ventricular valves closed
now here atrial ventricular
valves are closed at the
beginning of the ventricular
systole atrial pressure
slowly increases look at this
slowly increasing from x
descent it is increasing until
as the atria fill why does
it increase because atria
is filling which means
atria is receiving the blood
incoming blood creating the
baby that incoming blood
from the pulmonary veins
and the superior vena curva
that is increasing the
pressure as blood comes in
gradually pressure
increases that pressure
increase reaches a
point which is detected
as v-wave and once
it's filled then it
you see a y descent
and this y descent is
what is seen during
ventricular filling now this
ventricular filling phase
starts here and we will look
into these things in
greater detail this is
ventricular filling phase
okay from here to here this is
ventricular filling and
that happens when the AV
valves open atrio ventricular
valves are opening at
the beginning of the
ventricular filling and then
the atrial blood flows
into the ventricles because
atria has already received
the blood it flows into
ventricle and the atrial
pressure drops so as the
blood goes from atria to
the ventricle the blood
pressure the pressure of
the atrial chamber falls and
that is what is detected
as y descent okay and it
continues until when until
the next atrial contraction
begins and appears as a
wave but remember before a
wave appears your p wave
will appear okay all right
so what have you seen
so we have seen multiple
different waveforms going
back A wave C wave X descent
and then V wave and then Y
descent and when did this
become clinically important
you don't have to know
every possible clinical
condition but it's good to
remember few things as we
saw atrial fibrillation in
such a situation that can
be absent A wave. A wave
just can be simply absent
as in atrial fibrillation.
Flutter waves can
be seen in atrial
flutter and prominent
A waves can be seen in
first degree atrial
ventricular block.
Large A waves can be seen in
right atrial myxoma tumors
or even pulmonary hypertension,
pulmonary stenosis.
Absent X descent, absent
X descent can be seen
in tricuspid regurgitation
and then slow Y descent
can be seen in tricuspid
stenosis and rapid
Y descent. Like this
different things can be seen.
Cardiac tamponade can
have absent Y descent.
So you don't have
worry too much about
these things but
just understand,
frequently discuss
things like atrial
fibrillation where the
A wave can be absent.
So that's one important
clinical condition.
Okay now let's move on
to ventricular systole.
All right moving on
ventricular systole happens
between start of the QRS
complex and beginning of
the end of the T wave.
So here is the start of
the QRS complex and then
beginning of the end of
the beginning of the end
of the T wave okay this
is the T wave and this is
the T wave and beginning
of the end of the T
wave this is ventricular
contraction contraction
follows depolarization we know
there are three sub faces
of the ventricular system
and which are this is rapid
ejection this is reduced
ejection from here to here
is rapid this is to here to
here is reduced ejection and
then but before that it is
isovolumetric contraction
rapid ejection reduced
ejection before that the one
concept to understand is end
diastolic volume we will see
that in the second part
two we will see in greater
detail it is a volume of
blood in the ventricles at the
beginning of the ventricular
contraction at the beginning
of the systole how much
blood is remaining in the
heart that is end-diastolic
volume guided by Frank
Storing's law you will see
in the next part ventricular
systole I said isovolumetric
contraction is the first
sub phase of the ventricular
system here papillary
muscles initially contracting
both the valves are closed
and both ventricles are
closed blood filled chambers
again there is no air in any
time in the heart if there
is air that is a problem
that could lead to embolism.
So either the heart, you
know, reduces in size, which
means reduces volume, or
it increases. So since the
blood cannot be compressed,
the initial effect of
the ventricular contraction
is an increase in
intraventricular pressure. So
initially there is a surge in
ventricular pressure, sudden
increase in ventricular
pressure that happens.
Then the contract ejection
happens. So initially
isovolumetric, which means volume
remains the same and
dimension remains the same.
Why? The valves are still
closed. It has not opened
yet. So both the valves are
closed. Both the atrioventricular
valve and the semilinar
valves. Semilinar
valves are aortic and pulmonary
valves. Okay. Both are
Alright,
so next phase is still
isovolumetric contraction
is isometric and then
both the ventricles
develop enough pressure
to overcome their
respective afterloads
and in clinically in
catheterization laboratory
this can be measured as
DT by DT. It's the rate
of change of pressure.
Ventricular systole includes
the rapid ejection and
the second sub phase is
rapid ejection and reduced
rapid ejection where the
increase in ventricular pressure
continues and it exceeds
the arterial pressure.
Where is the arterial pressure?
This broken black line,
look, the red line which is
the LV pressure is slightly
to the left which means
it increases even little
more. It increases little
more than the aortic pressure
for a very brief period
of time and then it flips.
The ventricle pressure
continues to increase
after the aortic valve has
opened, or the pulmonary
valve has opened,
until it reaches a peak
point. What happens after
it reaches a peak point?
this is so far still in
rapid ejection phase is
isotonic contraction LV
pressure is slightly higher
than the blood pressure
LV pressure falls in
reduced ejection fraction
you can see that aortic
pressure continues to
rise high but it falls
slightly lower and it
continues to fall okay the
blood is still being ejected
and then that is reduced
ejection phase so the
inertia important by the
ventricular contraction
still continues to push
driving force of the
blood ejection but at one
point this phase stops when
the ventricular pressure
falls below the levels
needed to keep the aortic
valve and pulmonary valve
open and this coincides
with the T wave okay
this coincides with the
T wave. Here is the T
wave. I hope you can see.
Here is the T wave.
All right.
Let's move on.
Did we? Yes. Right. So,
so far we have seen what?
We have seen atrial
contraction, atrial systole,
atrial isovolumetric
contraction phase of ventricular
systole, rapid ejection
phase, and reduced ejection
phase of ventricular
systole. Again, all these
mechanical activity are preceded
by respective electrical
activity, P wave before
A wave, QRS before the
onset of the ventricular
contraction, okay, and then
just before the relaxation
begins, T wave happens,
which means T wave precedes
the ventricular relaxation.
A brief quick quiz
question here, take this
question, try to answer this,
okay, I'm going to say the
answer, so pause right now,
press your pause button
think and think what the
correct answer would be and
I will tell you the answer
the answer is D pressure
in the left ventricle
falls below the pressure in
the aorta okay I'll move
on in the interest of time
so ventricular diastole
ventricle diastole happens
beginning with the ice
again it divided into three
sub-phases one is
isovolumetric relaxation rapid
inflow and diastasis which
is reduced inflow so note
that ventricular diastole
starts with the closure
of the semilinear valves
semilinear valves are
aortic valve and pulmonary
valve we're talking about
the left side so aortic
valve closes closure this
is isovolumetric relaxation
begins pressure begins
continues to fall okay
until it reaches a point
where the atrioventricular
valve opens at the point
of the V wave we saw of
the atrial pressure curve.
Note that the volume
curve, right, the volume,
LV volume, the blue
one, increases with
atrial contraction we
saw. During isovolumetric
relaxation, the volume
remains unchanged.
That's why it's called
isovolumic or isovolumetric.
both contraction and
relaxation volume remains
the same but volume
reduces during ventricular
systole during both rapid
and reduced ejection that
is expected right logically
when the ventricle
is contracting pushing the
blood out volume reduces
and these can be measured
we'll talk about that
in the second session now
during relaxation after
the end of the isovolumetric
relaxation phase
the volume is going to
increase okay let's move on
isovolumetric relaxation it's
a fall in the ventricular
pressure following the
t-wave repolarization we
saw that the lv does not
completely empty during
ejection phase another thing
point to remember it doesn't
fully empty there is
blood remaining and that
remaining blood is called
end systolic volume which we
will understand more during
the second session And
systolic volume, and this
descent of the isovolumetric
relaxation, the pressure
descent, can be measured
in the laboratories,
clinical labs using DP by DT.
This is a mathematical
concept, but it's
automatically measured
using software programs.
Moving on, ventricular
diastole is a rapid filling
phase. Rapid filling phase,
what happens? The blood
surges in the ventricle,
volume increases very rapidly.
Pressure difference causes the
atrioventricular
valves to open.
The atrioventricular valves
open and it receives the blood.
And then the next phase
is reduced filling phase
where the blood
continues to increase but
not as rapid as it was in
the rapid filling phase.
So blood flow, the
ventricular diastolic
pressure is now lower
than the atrial pressure,
excuse me.
And then the ventricular
diastole transitions
into a slower reduced filling
phase called diastasis.
And the diastasis ends
with the P wave of the
next cycle. Where is the
P wave? Here is the P
wave. This P-wave, P-wave
is of the EKG. As the
P-wave happens, that's
when the diastasis phase
ends, and right after
the firing of the P-wave,
atrial pressure wave starts.
The ventricular
diastole ends with the
appearance of the
R-wave. Okay, good.
Alright, now we are
jumping into the new
concept of hot zones.
What are hot zones?
Hot zones happen, there
are four hot zones,
S1, S2, S3, and S4, you
may have heard already.
Now when the valves close,
the vanes of the valves
and the surrounding fluids
vibrate under the
influence of the sudden
pressure changes that
happen. and that's the reason
why we hear these sounds
during auscultation,
okay and that gives out
the sound that travels
in all directions
throughout the chest so
that's where we are able
to hear at different
points in the chest.
The mitral closure is
associated with a series
of broad low-pitched sounds
and that results in
the first heart sound,
okay and this is contrary
to the popular beliefs many
people think that the heart
sounds are due to flapping
or slapping of the valves
against one another that's
not the real reason it's
because of vibrations of
the blood okay all right so
having known that uh what
are the four heart sounds
s1 is associated with the
closure of the atrioventricular
valve and s2 is
associated with the closure
of the semilinal valves okay
closure of the semidina
valves here, and
closure of the
atrioventricular valve here.
That's S1 and S2.
S3 is seen, S1 and S2 is
seen in normal people,
right? S3 is the gallop
sound. S3 and S4 are
considered gallop sounds.
They are associated with
a rapid filling phase
of the ventricular
diastole. It's frequently
heard in normal children.
And S4 is associated
with atrial systole. it's
not seen here atrial
systole and diastolic it's
seen in some pathological
conditions such as
hypertrophied ventricle
various atrial
systole you can
see atrial systole
here and here okay
all right moving on
aortic pressure
aortic pressure is
This is the aortic pressure we
saw, the broken
top line, right?
Maximum, it can be
120. We saw 140 in
that figure, but
I also mentioned
120 is a reasonable
maximum estimate.
Rapid ejection phase.
During the rapid ejection
phase, we saw that LV
pressure is slightly higher
than the aortic pressure,
but it flips. During the
reduced ejection phase
the systolic aortic pressure
is higher than the ALB
pressure. Now there is this
and then aortic pressure
decreases but before
that there is a dichrotic
notch that is seen here.
This dichrotic notch or
incisura is caused by a
slight backflow aortic blood
that fills the semilinal
valve cusps as they close
okay now that's that's
about the aortic pressure
all right now moving on
the ventricular aortic
pressure and pulse pressure
right you would have you
would learn about pulse
pressure in the hemodynamic
lecture i believe so blood
flows to the arteries in
spurts and the aortic
pressure gradually decreases
and reaches its lowest
value 80 and once it reaches
lowest value it won't
continue to fall it will
again increase okay now
right-sided pressure is right
-sided pressure is just
to show give you an idea
the the pressure wave forms
are similar ACXVY atrial
pressure waveforms and
then right ventricle is
significantly higher systolic
is similar to pulmonary
diastolic is is, you know,
diastolic is, you know,
higher than the ventricular
diastole, and so on.
And then pulmonary
capillary wet pressure,
which is similar to the
right atrial pressure.
But look at the total,
the number itself on the
left side, on the y
-axis, it's not as high as
the left ventricle, that
is the point. And bottom
is the figure that we
have already seen before.
And here is a summary table.
I thought this could be
helpful. You can take
your time to read.
This is mostly what I
have already discussed
so far about the various
phases. On the left
you see atrial systole,
atrial isovolumetric
contraction,
rapid ventricular ejection,
rapid reduced ventricular
ejection, all these are
ventricular systolic phases,
and then we have isovolumetric
relaxation, rapid
fendling, and reduced filling,
these are all ventricular
diastolic phases. few things
that we didn't see or is
PR interval PR interval
can be is the time that's
more EKG concept right PR
interval ST segment is just
to give a context of where
the contractile or mechanical
event happening while PR
interval is happening it
is towards the final phase
of the ventricular filling
ST segment is when the
ventricles contract okay and
these are the position of
the valve or the status of
the valve. Mitral valve
closes here, aortic valve
opens here and so on. Fourth
heart zone we saw right.
Fourth heart zone
coincides with atrial
systole. First heart
zone with mitral valve
closure. Second heart
zone with aortic
valve closure. Third
heart zone if seen,
when seen coincides with
mitral valve opening.
Okay just keep understanding
these concepts and more
importantly I would say draw
the concepts okay draw the
concepts draw vigors diagram
hand draw if possible or
use an app or use a sketching
pad or something and
start drawing only when you
draw it becomes even more
it sticks even better okay
all right what does this slide
show this slide shows on
the top is the biggest
diagram of one heartbeat
right one heartbeat lasts for
about 0.8 to 0.9 seconds
okay in an adult adult human
now on the bottom you see
a loop right this is called
volume and pressure volume
loop which is what we are
going to see in the second
session this figure is just
to show that at different
phases of the cardiac cycle,
the loop, loops around
or at different phases
of the loop, different
points of the loop,
the heart is at
different time points
of the cardiac cycle.
Okay,
alright, no worries, we
will talk about this in
the second session. So
here is a quick sample
question, please take
your time to read this.
Let's read this together.
During ventricular
ejection phase, which of
the following statements
correctly describes
the valve movement?
You can take your
time to read A, B,
C, D, E. I'm going
to say the answer,
so please pause
right now to think.
And the answer is E.
The aortic valve is
open and the left
atrioventricular valve
is closed. That's
when, during ventricular
ejection phase,
this is what happens.
The aortic valve is
open and the left aortic
valve is closed. That
is when the blood
will go out into the
aorta, but it will not
go back into the atrium
under normal
healthy conditions.
But this is just for
practice, this is not in the
board style, so the questions
will be in board style.
I'm going to give some
more practice questions.
alright so what have we
seen so far so far we have
seen pressure volume changes
during each and every phase
of atrial ventricular
atrial systole and atrial
diastole and then ventricular
systole and ventricular
systole in a diastole in
normal cardiac cycle and within
that we saw sub phases
what are the sub phases
isovolumetric contraction sub
phase of ventricular eject
ventricular systole are
isovolumetric contraction,
isovolumetric, excuse me,
ventricular rapid
ejection and rapid reduced
ejection, excuse me.
And then ventricular
diastole, three sub-phases we
saw, one is isovolumetric
relaxation, rapid filling
and reduced filling,
also known as diastasis.
Heart valves,
different conditions,
status of the heart valve,
when is it open, when is
it closed we saw and then
EKG when it comes to EKG
remember the respective
electrical activity proceeds
so depolarization typically
precedes contraction
and then repolarization
precedes the relaxation of
the respective chambers and
then hard sounds we saw
one two three four and then
we looked all these things
in an integrative manner
using the vigors diagram
right good okay here are some
excuse me here are some
practice sample questions
these are some specific
questions in this google drive
link and then this is the
scholar products link they
also have some extra
questions for you to practice
okay with answers so first
practice without seeing the
answer of course and then
check the answers and then re
re-read re-test yourself
and that will help you make
it stick better all right
these are the reference
materials Guyton and Hall
have a newer edition now 14th
and 15th both similar chapters
mostly similar concepts
you can use any of these
links or both these links to
review you will have to
probably use your NYT login
to be able to view i believe
and sometimes copy paste
would be necessary rather
than directly clicking it
just copy paste this link to
be safe if it or if it doesn't
work and also scholar rx
brick will it can explain
it they may explain it
slightly you know differently
but it can add a different
perspective but they're
going to talk about similar
things in the cardiac cycle
Okay, I think that's pretty
much what I wanted to cover.
So if you have more questions,
you're welcome to email me,
okay. I hope
everything is clear.
I'm just scrolling
back to see if
there's anything
that I can add.
When you think about
this cycle, I pointed
out briefly, the whole
thing happens quickly.
The whole thing happens.
Each sub phase happens
in fractions of seconds,
for example, the atrial
systole itself takes
about 100 milliseconds.
You don't have to
memorize this, but just to
understand. and then the
rest of the atrial diastole,
the rest of it all is
atrial diastole, right,
which is about 800
milliseconds approximately,
and ventricular systole
is part of that,
so, and this keeps
happening constantly,
it keeps circling
again and again,
okay, so, what else can we add,
So, I think that's
pretty much it. If
you have more questions,
you're welcome
to contact me. I
think that's it.
And the clinical
case, we will talk
about the case in the
end of the session.
So, your job here is to
practice where the faces are.
so for example how can
question be sometimes questions
can be where is what's
happening to in which
phase you can see during
which phase you can see T
wave repolarization or P
wave electrical activity P
wave atrial depolarization
atrial depolarization
coincides with what or QRS
coincides with what remember
if P wave does not coincide
with atrial contraction
temporarily speaking P
wave coincides with more
of atrial diastole because
well atrial contraction
is atrial systole but P
wave has to fire before
right so it's coincides
more with atrial diastole
so like that you want to
think and then in what
phase does you can see
the heart valve excuse
me heart sound heard like
that you want to connect
between different things
happening in the heart
at a given point of
time okay I think that's
pretty much it best wishes
and we will see again